In the last video,
上一个视频中
we created this Panda series of a grocery list.
我们为杂货表创建了这么个 Pandas 序列
Now, how do we access or modify its elements?
那我们要如何访问或修改其中的元素呢？
One great advantage of the series object,
序列对象的一大优势在于
is that it allows us to access data in multiple ways.
允许我们以多种方法访问数据
One way is accessing elements with their index labels.
比如借助索引标签来访问元素
This accesses the quantity of eggs using the eggs label in square brackets.
这里在方括号中填写标签 eggs 就能访问鸡蛋数量了
We can get multiple elements by providing a list of index labels.
要访问多个元素 只需提供一个索引标签列表即可
Another way to access elements is numeric indices,
我们也可以用数字索引来访问元素
very similar to how we access elements in NumPy arrays.
这与我们访问 NumPy 数组元素的方法十分类似
Here, we get the quantity of the first item,
这里 我们以 0 为索引
eggs, using zero as our index.
访问了第一项 eggs (鸡蛋) 的数量
Now, let's get the last element with the index negative one.
现在 我们用索引 -1 来访问最后一个元素
And again, we can grab multiple items using a list of numerical indices.
跟之前一样 我们也可以用一个数字索引列表来访问多个项
In order to remove any ambiguity from rather we're referring to an index label,
为了避免我们在指明索引标签
or a numerical index,
和数字标签时有歧义
Panda series have two attributes loc,
Pandas 序列给出了两个属性 loc 以及 iloc
and iloc, to explicitly state what we mean.
来明确我们的意思
The attribute loc stands for a location,
属性 loc 表示位置
and it's used to explicitly state that we're using a labelled index.
用于指明我们用的是标签索引
Similarly the attribute iloc,
同理 属性 iloc
stands for integer location,
则表示整数位置
and is used to explicitly state that we are using a numerical index.
用于指明我们用的是数字索引
Panda series are also mutable like NumPy arrays,
Pandas 序列和 NumPy 数组一样是可变的
which means we can change the elements of a series after it's been created.
也就是说 序列创建后我们仍可以改变其中的元素
Let's change the number of eggs we need to buy from our grocery list.
我们来修改杂货表里要购入的鸡蛋数
Let's see our grocery list again.
这是刚才的杂货表
We can change the number of eggs from 30 to two by reassigning the element like this.
我们可以将鸡蛋数从 30 改为 2 只需像这样为元素重新赋值即可
Now, we can see that the data for eggs has been modified.
现在 我们可以看到鸡蛋的数据已经改好了
We can also delete items from a Panda series using the drop method.
我们还可以用方法 drop 来删除 Pandas 序列里的项
This method removes an element with the given label from the Panda series.
该方法会删除 Pandas 序列中与给定标签对应的元素
As you can see, apples is no longer included in the series returned by this method.
你可以发现 经该方法返回后 序列里就没有苹果了
However, this drops elements from the series out of place.
不过元素移除并不是在原序列中进行的
Meaning, up here, this just returned the modified series,
也就是说 这里返回的是经过修改的序列
and didn't actually change the original one as you can see here.
但不会改变原序列 如图
We can make this happen inplace,
我们也可以直接修改原序列
and change the original series by setting the parameter inplace to true.
只需将参数 inplace 设为 True 即可
Now, notice the drop method modified
注意 现在方法 drop
the actual series instead of returning another series with the modification.
修改的就是原序列了 而不是将修改后的版本以另一个序列的形式返回出来